A Guide to the John Z. Bowers papers FA1415
Rockefeller Archive Center
John Z. Bowers papers
circa 1858-1998
1950-1998
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bowers, John Z.
FA1415
23.03 Cubic Feet 37 letter-size boxes, 6 legal-size boxes, 1 half-letter-size box, 1 half-legal-size box, and 4 record carton storage boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
John Zimmerman Bowers was born on August 27, 1913 in Catonsville, Maryland. After graduating with his B.S. and M.D. from Gettysburg College and the University of Maryland, respectively, he served in the Naval Medical Corps during World War II. In 1945, before his discharge, Bowers spent six months at Harvard University training in pathology with Dr. Shields Warren, a noted pathologist and specialist in radiobiology.
In 1949, Bowers went to Japan to monitor the long-term biological effects of atomic radiation on the survivors of the attacks on Hiroshima and Nagasaki. This experience, and his later affiliation with the Radioactive Isotope Laboratory in Baltimore and the Crocker Radiation Laboratory of the University of California, Berkeley, led to his appointment in 1981 to the Advisory Committee to the Radiation Effects Research Foundation. He wrote a history of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission and the Radiation Effects Research Foundation (previously the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission).
Bowers' long-standing interest in Asia and Asian medicine led him to be awarded a China Medical Board fellowship to study medical education in Japan. Over the course of his life, he researched and wrote on medicine in Japan and China, of transitions and tensions between traditional and Western medicine, and medical education.
In 1965, Bowers became President of the Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation, which worked to advance education in the health sciences. Bowers organized and presided over several international conferences on medical care and education during his tenure at the Macy Foundation, which concluded with his retirement in 1980.
After his retirement, Bowers maintained his affiliation with the Rockefeller Foundation, which had begun in 1964, and served as a consultant. In 1983, he published The Health of Mankind, a history of the Foundation's health and natural science programs.
John Z. Bowers died in 1993.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The John Z. Bowers Papers were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by John Z. Bowers and later his wife, Akiko Bowers.
Related Materials
The Medical Center Archives of New York Presbyterian/Weill Cornell was donated in 2008 (see the John Z. Bowers Papers, Accession 2008:069).
Scope and Contents
The John Z. Bowers Papers document the research and writings of Bowers, a physician, educator, and expert on medicine and medical education, particularly in Japan and China. The papers include extensive research and reference materials that Bowers collected as he authored several books. These materials include articles, reprints, and translations, as well as Bowers' own notes and manuscripts.
While Bowers collected much of this information in his later years (1960s-1980s), some of the materials cover much earlier time periods, and a certain amount of the material is in other languages, including Japanese, Chinese, Portuguese, and Spanish.
Of particular interest is a small set of material gifted to Bowers by Dr. Shields Warren, including photographs of Nagasaki in 1947 and observations made during tests of the atomic and hydrogen bombs at Eniwetok/Enewetak in 1948.
Bowers also served as President of the Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation, and a portion of the collection includes published books which were the result of Macy-sponsored conferences.
Arrangement
The collection is generally arranged as received.
- Western Medicine in Japan, 2.46 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains research and reference materials related to Bowers' book on The Rise of Western Medicine in Japan. Files include reprints, articles, notes, and translations.
  - Neurology in Japan, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "The History of Neurology in Japan, with special reference to its postwar period" by Motoo Aki
  - Takano Choei - Gentō Fukushima, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "The Tragic Takano Choei Rangakusha / A Tragic Trangakusha, Takano Choei"
  - Takano Choei - Hagura, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notes on Kageyasu Takahashi Correspondence with Keisho Hagura On the Reconstruction of a Monument for Takano Choei
  - Takano Choei - Takano Choei (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Page and booklet re: Takano Choei Information on Takano Choei Memorials "Seiyō Gakushi so Setsu, The Theories of Western Philosophers" by Takano Choei
  - Takano Choei - Unfoldered Materials, 1967; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "The Spread of Western Science" by George Basalla "Lorenz Heister on Acupuncture: An Eighteenth Century View" by George Rosen
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Karl Meier-Lemgo, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Die Briefe Engelbert Kaempfers" by Karl Meier-Lemgo "Engelert Kämpfer (1651-1716)" by Karl Meier-Lemgo "Die Wirkung und Geltung Engelbert Kaempfers bei der Nachwelt" by Karl Meier-Lemgo JZB Notes
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - His Letters, Meier-Lemgo, 1969; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Notes on "Amoenitatum Exoticarum" preface Article on Loquats
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Bandar Abbas, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "Bandar Abbas" from Iran Airlines magazine
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Unicorn, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "The Unicorn and Other Lessons from History" by William J. Darby
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - "Uber die Echte Mumie und Uber den Medina-Wurm" by Karl Meier-Lemgo, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - "Kaempfer and the Lilies of Japan" by W.T. Stearn, 1948-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    "Kaempfer and the Lilies of Japan" by W.T. Stearn "A Brief Survey of Lily Literature" by William T. Stearn "Botanical Latin" by William T. Stearn
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Translations - The History of Japan (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Antique bookseller page on Engelbert Kaempfer
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - History of Goiter, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Correspondence with Isidor Greenwald "The Significance of the History of the Goiter for the Etiology of the Disease" by Isidor Greenwald
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Letters re: Purchase, 1723-1724 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Photograph copies of Kaempfer correspondence, British Museum
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - "Mechanism of Rhythmic Synchronous Flashing of Fireflies" by John and Elisabeth Buck, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    General
    Kaempfer quoted
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Sloane Letters - British Museum, 1725; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Translation comments, Zollman (1725) and Carrubba (1968)
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Trautz, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    "Kaempfer and Siebold" by F.M. Trautz
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - British Museum (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Notes on Kaempfer from British Museum, Sloane Archives
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - "Engelbert Kaempfer's Japanese Library" by K.B. Gardner, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Tropical Medicine History, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Notecards; "Aleixo de Abreu [1568-1630], Author of the Earliest Book on Tropical Medicine describing Ameobiasis, Malaria, Typhoid Fever, Scurvy, Yellow Fever, Dracontiasis, Trichuriasis and Tungiasis in 1623" by F. Guerra, 1968; "Concerning the Structure and Reproduction of the Guinea Worm (Filaria Medinensis L.)" by Aleksej Pavlovich Fedchenko, 1971
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Madura Foot, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    "Die Beschreibung des Madaurafußes durch Engelbert Kaempfer (1651-1716)" by Hermann Berger and Klaus Hesse
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - History of Tea, 1906-1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    "Tea Culture: The Tea-Culture in Java and Sumatra" by A.J. Garretsen (1929); Notecard and Notes; "Tea and Empire" by Shalleck; "The Book of Tea: The Tea-Room" by Kakuzo Okakura, ed. Everett F. Beiler, 1906, 1964
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Note on the Use of Cannabis in 17th Century, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    "A Note on the Use of Cannabis in the 17th Century" by John P. Dolan, 1971; "Religion and Medicine: The Chinese Opium Problem" by James F. Miskel, 1973
  - Engelbert Kaempfer - Am Ex References, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Notecards; Correspondence, University of California San Francisco Medical Center Archives (Luis Mercado and Marco Aurelio Severino); Correspondence with National Library of Medicine, Kaempfer; "Imaginary Beings," New Yorker
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Pompe Sensei and His Disciples, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Rijksarchief, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Correspondence from Algemeen Rijksarchief
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Utrecht Hospital, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    "Rijks-Kweekschool voor Militaire Geneeskundigen en Rijks-Hospital" by Wap; "State College for Military Physicians and State-Hospital" by Wap
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - "On the Study of the Natural Sciences in Japan" by Pompe Van Meerdervoort, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - "Achievement of Teacher Pompe, a Dutchman, in the Later Tokugawa Regime" by Numata Jirō, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Envelope, "Bakumatsu Ni Okeru Ranjin Kyoshi Pompe no Jiseki" (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Envelope, Picture of Utrecht Hospital, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Drawing of hospital
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - "Dissection of a Japanese Criminal" by Pompe Van Meerdervoort, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - "Verslag over de Gouvernements Geneeskundige dienst op het Eiland Desima en in Japan, over 1857 en 1858" by Pompe Van Meerdervoort (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Matsumoto Ryojun - Yamazaki Tasuku, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    "Pompe around November 12" by Yamazaki Tasuku
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Service Record, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Documentation on Pompe Van Meerdervoort; Correspondence on Pompe Van Meerdervoort to Karbaat, Jonkers
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Dutch Military Medicine, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    "De Historie van de Militair Geneekundige Dienst in Suriname" by J. Karbaat
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Chapter VI - Numata's Comments, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Jiro Numata, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    "Pompe Van Meerdervoort" by Jiro Numata
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Cornelius Ouwehand Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Correspondence between Bowers and Ouwehand
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Picture and Names, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Correspondence between Bowers and Ichiro Hayashi with photo of Pompe Van Meerdervoort
  - Pompe Van Meerdervoort - Pictures, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Pompe Van Meerdervoort courtesy of Michio Sato
  - Andreas Cleyer - "Christian Mentzel, Philippe Couplet, Andreas Cleyer und die Chinesische Medzin" by Eva Kraft, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Andreas Cleyer - "Flora Japonica", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Correspondence with Phyllis Edwards, British Museum (Natural History); "Flora Japonica"' "Medicine in the Service of the East-Indian Company in the Dutch-Indies," translation
  - Andreas Cleyer - Lemgo (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Postcards Brochures Photographs
  - Andreas Cleyer - Michael Boym (Box 2, Folder 45)
    "Boym and the Boymiae"
  - Andreas Cleyer - MS and Drawings, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Correspondence with Phyllis Edwards re: Cleyer
  - Andreas Cleyer - Moxa, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    "Sir William Temple and the Therapeutic Use of Moxa for Gout in England" by George Rosen
  - Ranzaburo Otori - "Acceptance of Western Cultures in Japan from the Sixteenth to the Mid-Nineteenth Century" by Ranzaburo Otori (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Ranzaburo Otori - Ranzaburo Otori (Box 2, Folder 49)
    "Western Books on Medicine Translated After Kaitai Shinsho, Modified from Otori, Ranzaburo: 'The Acceptance of Western Medicine in Japan'"
  - Siebold - Publications of Siebold (Box 2, Folder 50)
    "The Publications of Philipp Franz von Siebold"
  - Siebold - Notes on Juliuspital from Dieter Jetter, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Siebold - Siebold (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Notecards and Notes; Chronology; Outlines
  - Siebold - Sendai Hagi, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    "Kabuki" magazine
  - Siebold - Euro-Botany (Box 2, Folder 54)
    "Von Siebold and the Importation of Japanese Plants into Europe via The Netherlands" by J. MacLean
  - Siebold - Russian Voyages, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Correspondence from Jerry Stannard
  - Siebold - Acupuncture, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    "Some Observations about the Art of Acupuncture from a Letter of the Japanese-Imperial Acupuncturist Isi Saka Sotels" by Von Siebold; "Iets over de Acupunctuur (Naaldensteekkunde); Getrokken uit eenen brief van den Japansch-Keizerlijken Naaldensteker Isi Saka Sotels" by Von Siebold
  - Siebold - Siebold Letters, University of California Library, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Copies of Letters
  - Siebold - Envelope, Monograph on Siebold, Gift of Professor Otori, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Siebold - Return to Japan from Russia, Minami (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Chronology
  - Siebold - Ine and Taki-san Letters (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Siebold - Notes - Kyodai Lectures, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Manuscripts, Xerox, Kyodai
  - Siebold - Jardins des Plantes, Paris, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    Notes
  - Siebold - Nippon (Brunhuber) (Box 3, Folder 63)
    Quotes and Excerpts; "Beiträge zur Kenntnis der japanischen Akupunktur (Nadelstechkunde)"
  - Siebold - Letters, Folsom-Siebold (Box 3, Folder 64)
    Copies of Letters; Notes
  - Siebold - Josepha and Charlotte - Hans H. Lauer, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    "Zwei Mutige Frauen in Ihrer Zeit: Josepha von Siebold und ihre Tochter Charlotte Heidenreich-von Siebold"; "Two Courages Women in their Time: Josepha von Siebold and her daughter Charlotte Heidenreich-von Siebold" by Hans H. Lauer
  - Siebold - Siebold and Commodore Perry (Box 3, Folder 66)
    Rough Draft
  - Siebold - National Archives, Mr. Friis re: von Siebold (Box 3, Folder 67)
    Notes and Correspondence re: National Archives and Perry/von Siebold
  - Siebold - Naumann (Box 3, Folder 68)
    Correspondence and Notes from Naumann re: von Siebold
  - Siebold - Notes taken at von Siebold's Tomb, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Siebold - Steudel, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    "Die Siebolds, Ein hervorragendes Ärzte-Geschlect aud dem Dürender Lande" by J. Steudel; "The Siebolds - An Outstanding Family of Doctors from the Region of Dueren" by J. Studel
  - Siebold - Additional (Box 3, Folder 71)
    Notes, Copies, "Siebold and Dutch Djakarta" microfilm (separated)
  - Siebold - Archiv, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    "Siebold-Archiv"
  - Siebold - Batavia Archives (Boxer) (Box 3, Folder 73)
    Notes and Correspondence
  - Siebold - "Ein Artz als Kulturpionier" (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Siebold - Gerhard Fichtner (Box 3, Folder 75)
    "Philipp Franz von Siebold - Arzt und Japanforscher" by Gerhard Fichtner; Correspondence
  - Siebold - Genealogy (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Siebold - "De Historiae Naturalis in Japonia" (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Siebold - Heissig (Box 3, Folder 78)
    "Philipp Franz von Siebold: Ein Arzt schloß die Türen zum Verständis Japans auf" by Walther Heissig; "Philipp Franz von Siebold: A Physician Opened the Doors to the Understanding of Japan" (translation)
  - Siebold - National Archives Reference Service Report, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    Correspondence
  - Siebold - M. Hoyanagi, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    "Re-appreciation of Inō's Maps, the First Maps of Japan Based on Actual Survey" by Mutsumi Hoyanagi
  - Siebold - "Contes des Lundi" (Box 3, Folder 81)
    Notes, Translations
  - Siebold - Kabuki Play, "The Blind Emperor," K. Hidezo (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Siebold - "Hofreis" - Korner (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Siebold - Siebold Essays, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    "Philipp Franz von Siebold: A Contribution to the Study of the Historical Relations between Japan and the Netherlands"
  - Siebold - Korner's Notes (Box 3, Folder 85)
    Correspondence, Notes; "Philip Franz von Siebold: A Lifelong Love for Japan, Chapter VIII"
  - Siebold - Körner Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 86)
    Correspondence; "Philipp Franz von Siebold - Memorial on the Hundredth Anniversary of His Death, 18 October 1966 [sic.]"
  - Siebold - Numata [Kaempfer-Siebold] (Box 3, Folder 87)
    "Engelbert Kaempfer in Japan und Sein Einfluss auf Japan" by Jiro Numata
  - Siebold - "Kleiweg de Zwaan" (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Siebold - Leers (Box 3, Folder 89)
    "Der Japan-Siebold die Großleistung eines deutschen Arztes" by Johann v. Leers; "The Japan-Siebold: The Great Achievement of a German Physician" (translation)
  - Siebold - Letters to O-ine (Box 3, Folder 90)
    Correspondence, Notes, Copies
  - Siebold - Library of Congress (Mearns) Catalog Cards (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Siebold - Mittelbiberach Pictures and Notes (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Siebold - Nakanishi (Box 4, Folder 93)
    "Dr. P.F.B. von Siebold - A Short Chronicle of a German Doctor of the Romantic Period"
  - Siebold - Ogawa (Box 4, Folder 94)
    Correspondence and Notes; "Japanese Medical Journal no. 23"; Reprint
  - Siebold - Pen and Ink Portrait of Siebold (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Siebold - Perry (Box 4, Folder 96)
    "The Firest Japanese Embassy to the United States - 1860"; "Narrative of The Expedition of an American Soldier to the China Seas and Japan under the Command of Commodore M.C. Perry" by Francis L. Hawks (1856)
  - Siebold - Correspondence between William II and The Shogun (Box 4, Folder 97)
    "Correspondence between William II of HOlland and the Shōgun of Japan, A.D. 1844" by Greene; Photocopies, Letter from Mimamoto Iyeyasu (translation)
  - Siebold - Trautz (Box 4, Folder 98)
    Translation, "Kaempfer and Siebold" by F.M. Trautz
  - Siebold - W. Siebold (Box 4, Folder 99)
    Translation from "Ein Deutscher Gweinnt Japans Herz" by Werner Siebold (1943)
  - Siebold - Staatlichen Museum, Munich (Box 4, Folder 100)
    "Gedächtnisausstellung für den Japanforscher Philipp Franz von Siebold"
  - Siebold - Würzburg (Box 4, Folder 101)
    Postcards, Guidebooks
  - Ten Rhyne - Unfoldered Notes on John Ray and Ten Rhyne (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Ten Rhyne - Ten Rhijne, "Historische Schetsen" - Romer (Box 4, Folder 103)
    Notes, "Historische Schetsen Een Inleiding tot het Vierde Congres der Far Eastern Association of Tropical Medicine" by von Römer (1921)
  - Ten Rhyne - Ten Rhyne (Box 4, Folder 104)
    Notes and Biographical Information; Correspondence
  - Ten Rhyne - Ten Rhyne (Box 4, Folder 105)
    Biographical Information and Translations
  - Ten Rhyne - C.R. Boxer's Notes - Djakarta (Box 4, Folder 106)
    Correspondence and Notes
  - Ten Rhyne - Envelope, Dorssen (Box 4, Folder 107)
    Correspondence and Translations; "Willem Ten Rhijne" by J.M.H. van Dorssen
  - Thunberg - Unfoldered Materials, "Thunberg in Japan and His 'Flora Japonica' in Japanese" by Rudolph (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Thunberg - Letter to Linneaus (Box 4, Folder 109)
    Correspondence, Translation
  - Thunberg - Nils Svedelius (Box 4, Folder 110)
    "Carl Peter Thunberg, 1743-1828, Ett tvåhundraårsminne" by Nils Svedelius; "Dokt. Carl Peter Thunberg"
  - Thunberg - Letter to Thunberg (Box 4, Folder 111)
    Letter, Translation, Notes
  - Thunberg - Thunberg (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Titsingh - Unfoldered Page of Notes (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Titsingh - Illustrations of Japan - Reference Cards (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Titsingh - Letters to Isaac Titsingh (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Miscellaneous - Japanese Medical Schools, 1752-1850, Ogata and Shosendo (Box 4, Folder 116)
    Translations, Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous - Illustrations from Japanese Manuscripts, Wellcome Library (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Miscellaneous - Unfoldered Materials (Box 4, Folder 118)
    "Fukuzawa Yukichi to Sono Monka Shoshi" review; "Life of Sato Taizen" by Ogawa Twizo
  - Miscellaneous - History of Medicine in Japan, Vol. 2, Nihon Gakushi-on, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    Notes and Photocopies
  - Miscellaneous - Letter to Mrs. Minami, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Miscellaneous - G. Schurhammer, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Miscellaneous - Ishinho, Japanese Preference for Moxibustion (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Miscellaneous - Drugs from the Indies (Box 4, Folder 123)
    "Drugs from the Indies and the Political Economy of the Sixteenth Century" by Francisco Guerra
  - Miscellaneous - Nagasaki Reference Library (Box 4, Folder 124)
    Notes and Copies
  - Miscellaneous - Notes, Trip to Japan, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Miscellaneous - Bartolomeo Ōmura (Box 5, Folder 126)
    "Bartolomeo Ōmura: The Glory and Failure of a Christian Daimyō"
  - Miscellaneous - "Preparation for the Occupation of Japan" by Hugh Borton, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Miscellaneous - Y. Fujikawa (Box 5, Folder 128)
    "The Evolution of Japanese Medicine" by Y. Fujikawa - Notes
  - Miscellaneous - "Doctors of the Dutch Company in Japan" by Arnold Gubler (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - Miscellaneous - Seishu Hanaoka, Wakayama Medical Reports, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    "Seishu Hanaoka, Pioneer of teh [sic.] General Anesthesia and the Modern Surgery" by Hiromu Takebayashi
  - Miscellaneous - "Birth in Japan, around the Year, 'Hinoe-uma'" by Susumu Harashima (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - Miscellaneous - Jan Joosten, Seiichi Iwao (Box 5, Folder 132)
    "Jan Joosten" by Seiichi Iwao
  - Miscellaneous - "The Kaishihen," Yokohama Medical Bulletin, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    Notes; Vol. 18, Nos. 2 and 3
  - Miscellaneous - Montanus - Notecards (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - Miscellaneous - Nakayama (Box 5, Folder 135)
    "On the Introdution of Heliocentric System into Japan" by Shigeru Nakayama; "The First Appearance of Aristotelian Cosmology in Japan Kenkon Bensetsu" by Shigeru Nakayama
  - Miscellaneous - W. Schulze (Box 5, Folder 136)
    Copies of Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous - R.C. Rudolph (Box 5, Folder 137)
    "Illustrated Botanical Works in China and Japan" by Richard C. Rudolph; "Illustrations from Weinmann's 'Phytanthoza iconographia' in Iwasaki's 'Honzô zufu'" by Richard C. Rudolph
  - Miscellaneous - "Deutsche Ärzte in Japan als Mittler der abendländischen Medizin" by Johannes Steudel (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Miscellaneous - "What We Can Learn from Medical Education in the United States" (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - Miscellaneous - "The Transplantation of Modern Science and Technology into Japan" by Harumitsu Yoshimura (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Miscellaneous - Ogata Koan (Box 5, Folder 141)
    Notes, Clipping, Photograph; Reprint
  - Dejima - "The Historical Relations between Japan and The Netherlands" (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - Dejima - View of the Dutch Mansion at Dejima, Nagasaki Art Association (Box 5, Folder 143)
    "View of the Dutch Mansion at Dejima" (translation); Reprint
  - Rangaku - "A Bibliography of the Dutch Medical Books Translated into Japanese" by Saburô Miyasita (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - Rangaku - Kaitai Shinsho (Box 5, Folder 145)
    Newspaper article, "Western Medicine Here Owed Debt to 'Green-Tea Hag'" by Neil Pedlar
  - Rangaku - Michel Boym (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Rangaku - "Yamawaki Toyo" by H. Nishimura (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Rangaku - Yamawaki Toyo, W. Reinhardt (Box 5, Folder 148)
    Notes; "In Memory of Yamawaki Toyo, 200th Anniversary"; "Tamawaki Toyo, Anatomist, Philosopher, Physician, Poet, Scholar, Teacher" by William Reinhardt
  - Rangaku - Yamawaki Toyo, G. Achiwa (Box 5, Folder 149)